Cruiser Houston Collection, 1917-2003
University of Houston Libraries
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1932-2000
  - Letters
    - General
      - A.R. “Art” DuHaime to Robert Peary & his family, USS Houston Christmas card, San Francisco, California, December 7, 1941, with envelope. (Box 8, Folder 4)
        Donor: Robert Peary
      - Paul Erickson to Otto Schwarz, Jakarta, Indonesia, April 28, 1992. (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Tom Falloon to Otto Schwarz, March 27, 1994,, with photograph of Arthur and Betty Maher, postcard, and obituary for Arthur Maher (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Larry [B. Grant] to Otto Schwarz, April 23, 1980. Donor: Otto Schwarz Helen I. Gould to F.B. Simms, Wichita, Kansas, August 8, 1947 (carbon copy), with affidavit (copy and carbon copy) and notes. (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Harold S. Hamlin, Jr. to Mrs. Ellis, Washington D.C., October 23, 1945. (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Harold S. Hamlin, Jr. to Mr. & Mrs. Kondzela, Washington D.C., October 23, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 4)
        Donor: Harold S. Hamlin
      - Mrs. Thomas C. (Caroline B.) Hart to Otto C. Schwarz, Sharon, Connecticut, April 1, 1980. (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Mrs. Thomas C. (Caroline B.) Hart to Otto [Schwarz], Sharon, Connecticut, April 16, 1981. (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Harold J. “Hap” Heidel to Otto [Schwarz], New Leston, Wisconsin, June 10, 1986. (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Fred G. Hodge to Edith Rooks, Portland, Oregon, August 27, 1945, with Exchange of Information Sheets (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - John Wm. “Bill” Hollingsworth to Dr. & Mrs. J.L. Kinkaid, Great Lakes, Illinois, August 13, 1940, with envelope (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - John Wm. “Bill” Hollingsworth to Dr. & Mrs. J.L. Kincaid, Great Lakes, Illinois, [September 5, 1940], with envelope (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - John Wm. “Bill” Hollingsworth to Dr. & Mrs. J.L. Kincaid, Great Lakes, Illinois, September 17, 1940, with envelope (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Bill [Hollingsworth] to Dr. & Mrs. J.L. Kincaid, Great Lakes, Il., September 19, 1940 (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - John Wm. “Bill” Hollingsworth to Dr. & Mrs. Kincaid, Mare Island, California, September 30, 1940 (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - John Wm. “Bill” Hollingsworth to Dr. & Mrs. J.L. Kincaid, Asiatic Station, December 31, 1940 (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - John William “Bill” Hollingsworth to Dr. & Mrs. J.L. Kincaid, Manila, Philippine Islands, June 15, 1941 (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - John D. H. Kane, Jr. to Otto C. Schwarz, Washington D.C., March 4, 1980. (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - W.A. Kirkland to Officer of Deck, USS Houston [CL-81], Houston, Texas, October 31, 1945. (Box 8, Folder 5)
        Donor: Allie V. Layne
      - Joe Kollmyer to Department of the Army, San Angelo, Texas, December 11, 1988 (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 5)
        Donor: Joe Kollmyer
      - Joe Kollmyer to William E. Ryan, Jr., San Angelo, Texas, September 29, 1988 (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - M.R. Lenci to Mr. [Otto] Schwarz, San Francisco, California, March 15, 1993, with letter from M.R. Lenci to Houston parents. (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Lorie, All Faith Monument Works, to Otto Schwarz, Newfoundland, New Jersey, September 28, 1994. (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Ken Lowman to Mrs. Keith, August 27, 1946 (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - James McCone to Otto Schwarz, Arlington, WV, September 26, 1989. (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Ross T. McIntire to Mrs. Ora Magelene Ellis, Washington D.C., September 5, 1946. (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - A.L. Maher to Mrs. Jones, Washington D.C., November 14, 1945 (photocopy), with biographical account of William S. Jones. (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - A.L. Maher to Mr. White, Washington D.C., November 14, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - M.J. Mayer to Otto Schwarz, USS Chosin,March 6, 1991. (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - John F. Manning to Joe Kollmyer, Alexandria, Virginia, January 3, 1989, with case findings for Francis B. Weiler. (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Irene Mills to Mr. [Otto Schwarz], undated, with envelope. Donor: Irene Mills (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Irene Mills to Mr. [Otto Schwarz], Cincinnati, Ohio, April 27, 1981. (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Thomas B. Payne to Otto [Schwarz], Coronado, California, January 25, 1990. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - R.N. “Sonny” Robertson to Sister & Jim, Pearl Harbor, March 8, 1940. (Box 8, Folder 6)
        Donor: James R. Darden and Bonnie J. Fields
      - [R.N.] “Sonny” [Robertson] to Madeline &Jim, Manila, P.I., March 2, 1941. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - R.E. “Gene” Peterson to Elinore Peterson, USS Houston, May 7, 1941, with envelope. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - [R.E.] “Gene” [Peterson] to [Mrs. R.N. Peterson], Manila, P.I., June 21, 1941. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - [R.E.] “Gene” [Peterson] to Mother, Manila, P.I., June 26, 1941. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - [R.E.] “Gene” [Peterson] to Mother, Cebu, Cebu, P.I., August 16, 1941. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - R.E. Peterson to Mother, Tui Tui Bay, August 19, 1941. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - [R.E.] “Gene” [Peterson] to Mother, Cavite, P.I., November 22, [1941]. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - R.H. “Bob” Pullen to Carol Pullen, Asiatic Station, June 27, 1941, with envelope. (Box 8, Folder 6)
        Donor: Carol Pullen
      - Capt. A[lbert] H. Rooks, Operations for December 21, 22 and 23, 1941 (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 6)
        Donor: Matthew L. Johnson
      - William E. Ryan, Jr. to Joe Kollmyer, Washington D.C., November 26, 1988 (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Otto C. Schwarz to Elizabeth Wachendorfer, Union, New Jersey, November 1992, with note from Otto [Schwarz] to Liz [Wachendorfer], November 18, 1992, and excerpts from Blue Bonnet (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Otto C. Schwarz to Paul Hidalgo, February 15, 1980, carbon copy. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Otto [Schwarz] to Shipmates, Union, New Jersey, February 20, 1980 (two copies). (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Otto Schwarz to Mrs. [Thomas C.] Hart, April 8, 1980, carbon copy. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Otto Schwarz to Paul Erickson, Union, New Jersey, June 19, 1992. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - F.B. Simms to Helen I. Gould, Washington D.C., March 20, 1947. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - F.B. Simms to Helen I. Gould, Washington D.C., May 9, 1947. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Harry Truman to George Elen Detre, Washington [D.C.], November 15, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Harry Truman to William John Stewart, Washington [D.C.], November 27, 1945, with envelope. (Box 8, Folder 7)
        Donor: William J. Stewart
      - J.W. Vogan to Mrs. F.D. (Ora) Ellis, Goodland, Kansas, February 1, 1944. (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Elizabeth Wachendorfer to Otto C. Schwarz, Houston, Texas, December 14, 1992 (photocopy) (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - G.A. Wallace to Thomas B. Payne, San Francisco, California, March 2, 1992. (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Madeline Day Wassell to Mrs. R.B. (Ruth) Ansell, Los Angeles, California, March 19, 1944, with envelope. (Box 8, Folder 7)
        Donor: Eugene Crispi
      - Richard L. Wilson to J.B. Soedarmanto Kadarisman, Jakarta, Indonesia, April 30, 1992, with Diplomatic Note No. 204. (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Sidney Winoker to Paul Hidalgo, Winter Haven, Florida, February 6, 1980 (photocopy). (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - John and Iku Wisecup to Frank Gallagher, Yokohama, Japan, July 23, 1996, with envelope. (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - John and Iku Wisecup to Frank Gallagher, Yokohama, Japan, February 14, 1997, with envelope. (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - [John Wisecup] to Frank E. Gallagher Jr., Yokohama, Japan, November 16, 1997, with envelope. (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - [John Wisecup] to Frank E. Gallagher Jr., cartoons, clipping, envelope, etc., [circa 1996-1997]. (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - John and Iku [Wisecup] to Otto [Schwarz], Yokohama, [Japan], September 15, with photocopied poems and other materials. (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Hunter Wood, Jr. to John G. Robertson, Washington D.C., August 7, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Envelopes
      - Commemorative and postmarked envelopes, three, 1932-1934. (Box 8, Folder 8)
        Donor: Allen Crispi
      - Commemorative envelope, 1935. (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Commemorative envelopes, 1936-1939. (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Commemorative envelopes, forty-five, 1936-1995 (including five photocopies). (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Commemorative envelopes, three, 1939 and ca. 1939 (Box 8, Folder 10)
        Donor: Harold Page
      - Commemorative envelope,. [1942] [1942] (postmarked 1987) (Box 8, Folder 10)
        Donor: Ralph H. Lovett, Sr.
      - G.E. Detre to Mr. & Mrs. C.G. Detre, Manila, P.I., December 8, 1941. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - [Arthur DuHaime] to Veronica DuHaime, commemorative envelope, Vallejo, California, September 10, 1940. (Box 8, Folder 10)
        Donor: Art DuHaime
      - F.D. Ellis to Mrs. F.D. Ellis, commemorative envelope, Manila, P.I., Dec. 8, 1940. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - F.D. Ellis to Mrs. F.D. Ellis, commemorative envelope, Manila, P.I., Dec. 15, 1940. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - [Thomas Falloon] to Dorothy Perotti, Christobal, C[anal] Z[one], April 26, 1934. (Box 8, Folder 10)
        Donor: Thomas Falloon
      - [Thomas Falloon] to Dorothy Perotti, San Juan, P.R., July 7, 1934. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - [Thomas Falloon] to Dorothy Perotti, Cartagena, Columbia, July 10, 1934. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - [Thomas Falloon] to Dorothy Perotti, Balboa, Canal Zone, July 12, 1934. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - [Thomas Falloon] to Dorothy Perotti, Honolulu, T.H, July 28, 1934. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - [Thomas Falloon] to Dorothy Perotti, Portland, Oregon, August 3, 1934. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - William O. Frederick to Jo Robertson, commemorative envelope, Long Beach, CA, May 1, 1939. (Box 8, Folder 10)
        Donor: Gary E. and Gregory P. White
      - William O. Frederick to Jo Robertson, commemorative envelope, Bremerton, WA, July 25, 1939. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - William O. Frederick to Jo Robertson, commemorative envelope, September 13, 1939. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - [Herb Herman] to Minerva G. Cato, commemorative envelope, Seattle, Washington, August 8, 1935. (Box 8, Folder 10)
        Donor: Herb Herman
      - [Herb Herman] to C.A. Emerson, USS Houston, June 22, 1938. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - [Herb Herman] to W.A. Mealey, Honolulu, T.H., July 28, 1934. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - [Herb Herman] to Nell Horowitz, USS Houston, June 17, 1935. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - [Herb Herman] to Nick J[r.], commemorative envelope, USS Houston, February 23, 1936. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - [Herb Herman] to Nick Jr., commemorative envelope, USS Houston, March 6, 1936. (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Mrs. J. Nickel to Henry Nickel, Dinuba, California, December 30, 1943. (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Claude Eugene Parker to Mr. & Mrs. Forrest Duncan, Asiatic Station c/o San Francisco, December 8, 1940. (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - R.E. Peterson to Mrs. R.N. Peterson, Asiatic Station c/o San Francisco, California, May 26, 1941. (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - R.E. Peterson to Mr. Lillian Peterson, Asiatic Station c/o San Francisco, California, July 16, 1941. (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - R.E. Peterson to Mrs. R.N. Peterson, Asiatic Station c/o San Francisco, California, July 30, 1941. (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - R.E. Peterson to Mrs. Lillian Peterson, commemorative envelope, Asiatic Station, September 19, 1941. (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - R.E. Peterson to Mrs. Lillian Peterson, Asiatic Station c/o San Francisco, California, September 19, 1941. (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - R.E. Peterson to Mrs. Lillian Peterson, commemorative envelope, Asiatic Station, October 11, 1941. (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - [Otto Schwarz] to Elizabeth Wachendorfer, two commemorative envelopes, Perth, Australia, February 28, 1992. (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - [William Slough] to O.E. Baer, San Diego, California, August 18, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - William Slough to Mrs. O.E. Baer, San Francisco, California, December 10, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - William Slough to Mrs. O.E. Baer, San Francisco, California, March 7, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - John Stefanek to Mr. & Mrs. Al Stefanek, commemorative envelope, Manila, P.I., 1941. (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - To G.F.J. von Hoffman, commemorative envelope, May 31, 1934. (Box 8, Folder 11)
        Donor: Joe Schroeder
- DIARIES, 1941-[1945]
  Diaries are organized alphabetically by the name of the person who kept the diary. Original diaries from the 1940s are very fragile. Patrons in our reading room will be given a photocopy of Brigadier Arthur Varley’s diary to use in order to protect the original.
  - Address book and log, [1942-1945]. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Arthur Bancroft, HMAS Perth, 1942-1944 (photocopied transcript), with note. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Donor: Clarence Schilperoort
  - Herbert A. Levitt, [1942-1945]. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Donor: The Levitt family
  - Quentin C. Madson, November 27, 1941 – May 14, 1942, and The Cruise of the Flagship Houston [poem] by Lloyd Willey [1941-1945], with note. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Donor: Quentin C. Madson
  - Quentin C. Madson, November 27, 1941 – May 14, 1942 (transcript). (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Quentin C. Madson, expanded version of transcript, November 27, 1941 – May 14, 1942 (photocopy). (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - James E. Reynolds, reconstructed account for December 1941 – October 1942; diary for November 1942 – August 1943. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Donor: James E. Reynolds
  - James E. Reynolds, September 1943 - October 1945. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - James E. Reynolds, September 1943 – October 1945 [microfilm] (Box 64)
  - The Story of the USS Houston, compiled by officers, chiefs, and petty officers in Batavia, Java, April 1942 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - [USS Texas (BB-35)], June 6, [1944] - September 2, [1944] (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Brigadier Arthur Varley, Australian Army, May 12, 1942- March 26, 1944 (photocopy). (Box 10, Folder 1-7)
    Donor: Mrs. Marvin E. Robinson
  - Brigadier Arthur Varley, Australian Army, May 12, 1942- March 26, 1944. (Box 10, Folder 8-20)
- BLUE BONNETS, 1933-2003
  The Blue Bonnet was the shipboard newsletter for the USS Houston (CA-30) crew. This series includes Blue Bonnets from the ship for the years 1933 through 1941, although not all issues are available. The Blue Bonnets from the 1930s are very fragile, and most of them have been photocopied. Patrons in our reading room will be given photocopies of some issues to read rather than originals.
  In the late 1940s, Otto Schwarz of the USS Houston Survivors Association revived the Blue Bonnet as that organization’s newsletter. Newsletters from the survivor’s organization include issues from 1960 through the present.
  Between 1991 and 1997, a separate newsletter was put out by the Next Generation (a related association for the children and other family members of survivors). That newsletter was discontinued, and as of 1998, the Blue Bonnet has served as the organ for both the Survivors Association and the Next Generation. Recent copies of the Blue Bonnet can be found on the web site http://www.usshouston.org.
  - Blue Bonnet, July 1, 1933; March 28, 1936. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1934(reference photocopy) (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1934. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Blue Bonnet, Jan. – July 1935 (reference photocopy) (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Blue Bonnet, Jan. – July 1935. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Blue Bonnet, Aug. – Dec. 1935 (with reference photocopies). (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Blue Bonnet, Jan. – Aug. 1936 (reference photocopy) (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Blue Bonnet, Jan. – Aug. 1936. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Blue Bonnet, Aug. –Dec. 1936. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Blue Bonnet, Jan. – June 1937 (with reference photocopies). (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Blue Bonnet, June – Dec. 1937 (with reference photocopies). (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Blue Bonnet, Jan. – May 1938. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Blue Bonnet, June – Dec. 1938. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Blue Bonnet, Jan. – May 1939. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Blue Bonnet, June – Dec. 1939. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Blue Bonnet, Jan. – June 1940. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Blue Bonnet, July – Dec. 1940. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Blue Bonnet, July 15, 1940. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Blue Bonnet, March 27, 1940; May 11, 1940; June 17, 1940. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Blue Bonnet, Jan. – May, 1941. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Blue Bonnet, Feb. 1960; ca. Sept. 1982; June 1983; July 1984. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Blue Bonnet, June 1975 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Blue Bonnet, Nov. 1978. (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Blue Bonnet, with Artifacts and Memorials booklet; Ship’s Bell booklet, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1999 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Blue Bonnet, 2000 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Blue Bonnet, 2001 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Blue Bonnet, 2002 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Blue Bonnet, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Blue Bonnet: The Next Generation,, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Blue Bonnet: The Next Generation,, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Blue Bonnet: The Next Generation,, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Blue Bonnet: The Next Generation,, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Blue Bonnet:The Next Generation,, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Blue Bonnet: The Next Generation,, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 20)
- DECK LOGS, 1940-1942
  As defined by the Naval Historical Center, “A Navy ship's deck log is a daily chronology of certain events for administrative and legal purposes.” The USS Houston (CA-30) deck logs in this collection are photocopies of the originals, which are held by the National Archives at College Park, Maryland. The deck log for February 1942 was reconstructed by Lt. Cmdr. Harold S. Hamlin and submitted to the Bureau for Naval Personnel in September 1945.
  A few deck logs for the USS Mount Vernon and the USS Tulsa can be found in the Documents series.
  - Deck log, November 1940 (photocopy). (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Deck log, December 1940 (photocopy). (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Deck log, January 1941 (photocopy). (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Deck log, February 1941 (photocopy). (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Deck log, March 1941 (photocopy). (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Deck log, April 1941 (photocopy). (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Deck log, May 1941 (photocopy). (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Deck log, June 1941 (photocopy). (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Deck log, July 1941 (photocopy). (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Deck log, August 1941 (photocopy). (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Deck log, September 1941 (photocopy). (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Deck log, October 1941 (photocopy). (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Deck log, November 1941 (photocopy). (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Deck log, November 1941 (photocopy). (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Deck log, December 1941 (photocopy). (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Deck log, January 1942 (photocopy). (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Reconstructed deck log (February 1942), 1945 (photocopy). (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Reconstructed deck log (February 1942), 1945 (photocopy). (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Deck log [microfilm] (Box 64)
- REPORTS, [ca. 1942]-1947
  This series includes primarily official government reports, among them Action Reports and Battle Damage Reports for the USS Houston (CA-30) and the USS Houston (CL-81). Reports are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Action Report Covering Evacuation of Prisoners of War During Period 29 August 1945 to 19 September 1945, September 22, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 15, Folder 6)
    Donor: USS San Juan Shipmates
  - Action Report of the USS Houston (CA-30) in defense of convoy off Darwin, Australia, November 14, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Action Report - USS Houston (CA-30) on the Battle of Sunda Strait, November 20, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Battle Damage to USS Houston (CL-81), January 6, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Battle Damage to USS Houston (CL-81), February 14, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Battle Summary: Battle of the Java Sea, 1945 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Engagement off Soerabaja, [ca. 1945] (photocopy). (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Medical Experiences With POWs in Malaya, Burma, and Siam (photocopy), [ca. 1942]. (Box 15, Folder 13-15)
  - Medical Experiences With POWs in Malaya, Burma, and Siam, [ca. 1942]. (Box 15, Folder 16-23)
  - Military Court For the Trial of War Criminals: Major Mizutani Totare, 1946 (photocopy from Navy Dept.) (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Pay & Treatment of Officer Prisoners of War, December 27, 1944, and other documents (photocopy from Navy Dept.) (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Report of Salvage of USS Canberra and USS Houston, November 30, 1944 (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Rough Translation of Official Japanese Account of The Battle of Sunda Strait, undated. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - [USS Houston (CA-30) Battles of Java Sea and Sunda Strait Report] (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - USS Houston (CL-81) - Action Report for Saipan-Tinian-Guam Operation, August 21, 1944 (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - USS Houston (CL81) Battle Damage, January 20, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - USS Houston (CL-81) - Bombardment of Angaur, Peleliu, and Ngesebus, Palau Islands, September 10, 1944 (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - USS Houston (CL-81) - Bombardment of Rota and Guam (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - USS Houston (CL-81) - Report of Actions Occurring 12, 13 and 14 October 1944, October 20, 1944 (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - USS Houston (CL-81) - Report of Action Occurring on 16 October 1944, October 29, 1944 (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - USS Houston (CL-81) - Torpedo Damage Off Formosa, March 15, 1947 (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 12)
- STATEMENTS, 1945-1950
  This series includes official statements and casualty affidavits given by Houston crew members following their liberation from POW camps. Statements are arranged alphabetically by the name of the person who gave the statement, or the subject of casualty affidavit.
  - E. M. Barrett, USMC, undated (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - R. C. Calloway casualty affidavit, [ca. 1945], (photocopy from Navy Dept.) (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - A. R. Demoen, September 9, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 15)
    Donor: Archiel R. Demoen
  - Enclosure A to Alonslo Calcutta, September 11, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - William A. Epstein, [ca. 1945], (photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - William A. Epstein, [ca. 1945], (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Harold S. Hamlin, regarding Lawrence Richard Wargowsky, 1950 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Harold S. Hamlin, Report of Service as Prisoner of War, [ca. August 30, 1946], (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Harold S. Hamlin, September 14, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 21)
  - Harold S. Hamlin, September 14, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - Harold S. Hamlin, [ca. October 1945] (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 23)
  - W. D. Haskell casualty affidavit, [ca. 1945] (photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 24)
  - Eugene E. Lehnoff, MIS-X Questionnaire, [1945] (photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 25)
  - Arthur Lawrence Maher, December 5, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 26)
  - S. Martin casualty affidavit, [ca. 1945], (photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 27)
  - Milton Robert May casualty affidavit, [ca. 1945], (photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 28)
  - Commander Rentz casualty affidavit, [ca. 1945], (photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 29)